Hello everyone welcome to Transforming 360
and today's video is on the detailed health insurance
concept as you have repeatedly demanded the
concept of how the health insurance concept
works,
so I will give you for example like the body
is a human body and the common thing in it among
all the humans is the
skeleton and what is a skeleton, it is a
structure and on which if we
create different features then different
types of people are created, if we
paint it white then it will become fair, if we paint it black then it will become
black, so such features work
but the skeleton is the main
base, similarly
today we will discuss the main base of health insurance so that you
people can get clarity on the concept that why
health insurance is important and
what is actually the purpose of health
insurance,
so today we are
healthy that means we are eligible for health
insurance but God forbid after the next 5 years,
2 years, 10 years I face the problem of hospitalization, then
health
insurance will be there  It will be useful and the hospitalization is of
two types, it happens in two ways,
one is
emergency and second is post hospitalization treatment,
when we talk about emergency, that means
sudden heart attack accident in those cases, then
two things are covered there, one is the
hospitalization part which needs minimum 24
hours of hospitalization and other wise day
care procedures, so one is that
hospitalization part and second is that
post hospitalization,
after getting treatment in the hospital, when you are discharged, then even
after that the treatment
expenses are incurred, so post hospitalization
means that even after getting discharged, the
continuous treatment which is
covered in the policy is covered on the policy
term and condition, so some policies cover it for 60 days,
some cover it for 90 days
and some cover it for 180 days also
and there are three major expenses
which are covered in it, one is doctor visit,
second is our diagnosis test and all and
third is medicine, so these three things are
covered under post hospitalization  I am
talking about the second type of
hospitalization, that is plan
hospitalization. In that situation,
three things are covered, so
expenses are incurred even before going to the hospital. For
example, today I am feeling some problem in my heart, I am feeling suffocated.
I got the treatment done, the doctor did a
checkup, got the tests done, gave medicines and
then after a month he felt that no, we have to go
for surgery. So that means expenses are incurred
even before hospitalization. That is
called pre-
hospitalization. Pre-hospitalization
expenses are the
expenses incurred even before getting admitted through hospitalization. It is also
covered if there is hospitalization. If this
claim is payable then this claim is also
payable and this varies from policy to policy. There are some
companies which are
covering for 30 days pre-hospitalization.
Some companies cover for 60 days and some
cover for 90 days also. So, second is
hospitalization and third is
post-hospitalization, same as
in case of emergency, after discharge.  Even after that, the
after care treatment expenses are covered.
So today let us understand a little about
what all
expenses are incurred in hospitalization and why health insurance is important.
So when we are hospitalized, the
first expense that comes up is the road
ambulance to
reach the hospital. We have to pay ambulance
charges and that is on average ₹
000. This is also covered by health insurance. The
first expense is the ambulance charge. Now if we
go there for a check-up, then the
consultation charges may be ₹2000 depending on the
hospital. Now they have to diagnose the patient and they have to
give medicines as well. Diagnosis has to be done. So
initially, there can be multiple
tests like CT scan, MRI, BT, Echo and
it may be other tests and blood
test. So its average cost comes to minimum ₹00.
Now let us talk about the next expense.
So that is the medicine part. That is ₹2000,
3000, 4000 depending on the scenario. Now comes the
admission charges. Now we know that now this
hospitalization needs further.  If
we look at the examination, what does the hospital
do? If it admits the patient, then the admission fee
charges are on average 000, which is also
covered by the health insurance
company. Now if we go a little deeper, then the
room rent
charges will depend upon the standard of the
hospital. So the average costing is
00, it is also covered by 00 per day charges.
Now as the room rent becomes expensive,
accordingly there will be doctor fees, consultation and nursing
charges. These proportional
charges also vary depending on your room rent
and the room category.
Now the room rent comes to 10,000. So the
next expense that comes is
for doctor visit. The doctor visits two times a day. On an
average, 1500 to 000 per visit
charges are charged by the doctor from the hospital. This comes
to 3000 and 4000 depending
upon the
hospital. Then comes the nursing
charges. Nursing charges are half of the doctor visit
and in a day  There are
three nursing visits within 24 hours, so three
visits for 88 hours, three shifts, so that
means if there is also nursing charges, that means it comes down
to
000, next charge then again diagnostic,
that too daily, our diagnostic will
come out every morning, then there will be tests, examination to see what improvement is happening,
so in the hospital it may cost
10000, in the hospital it may cost 000, in the hospital it may cost 5000
depending upon the type of
hospitalization, now the next expense comes that is
for surgery, now it becomes clear that
we will have to go for surgery, in that
situation if that thing
can be cured without surgery in the evaluation, then
that cost will be incurred and you will come
out after being discharged, but
if we have to go for surgery, then the first
costing is
anesthesia and until the surgery is not done, the
surgery cannot be done, so the average
fee for the surgery is 25000,
second charge is for surgery cost,
now what is the surgery cost, how will the surgery cost  The cost will depend on the size of the surgery
being done. If it is a gold butter
surgery, it may cost Rs 50,000. If it is a slightly
bigger surgery, it may cost Rs 1 lakh. If
it is a bigger surgery, it may cost Rs 3 lakh. If it is a
bigger
surgery, it may cost Rs 15 lakh. And if the surgery is bigger than that, it may cost Rs 1 lakh. And then the surgery will also cost more than Rs
lakh. So one is the surgery charges, then the surgeon
cost, the
doctor who is performing the surgery procedure, his charges, his
fees, is on
average Rs 15 to 20 per day.
Now, if the surgery is successful, then
where will you shift after the surgery,
in the ICU, so the costing of ICU is
almost double the room rent, so Rs 100 per day.
Now, it depends on how the situation is, for
how many days one may have to stay in the ICU.
Now, after the ICU, if the situation is a little
critical, then out of compulsion, one has to shift to a
ventilator. So, ventilator
charges are almost double of ICU charges,
that means  00 average and in Covid, people have paid
more than one lakh rupees per day charges for ventilator.
Now till here we are talking about surgery,
now after this comes the normal room rent, then we
shift to the same again per day
00, followed by the diagnostic
medicine charges, doctor visit, nursing
charges, its per day cost is a fixed
cost, now going further
and surgery, one more thing to be kept in mind,
nowadays robotic surgery is happening through advanced
technology, which is also
covered by some companies and whose charges are
more than the normal charges,
so it is also covered by health
insurance, so if we look at the average total costing,
then only if
we
look at the hospitalization for 10 days and
exclude the surgery, then per day room rent comes to Rs 10000 on
average, per day for
hospitalization for 10 days, then doctor
visit Rs 3000 per day, multiply by 10 days,
30000 nursing charges  1000 per visit per day that means
3000 Malla by 10 days
diagnostic on average we also take 5000 per
day so it comes to
0000 then
admission charges ICU charges
ventilator charges
then medicine
charges then after that we will add
asia plus surgery cost plus surgeon
fee and plus care
cost so minimum 10 days
hospitalization costs 1 lakh rupees for normal
treatment but if the same situation is
critical then if we talk about
kidney then single kidney removal
surgery costs 1 lakh but
if kidney transplant surgery is
going to
cost minimum 15 lakh rupees on average and in which
harvesting and donor cost are not included
liver
transplant charges 4 to 4 lakh rupees on average
very few hospitals who are capable for
these surgeries specifically for liver
transplant, heart transplant, major
organ transplant, deep brain
surgeries so first  We have to understand that
if you see that till now we have visited a hospital because till now
90% of us would be such people
who would have never gone to a hospital and even if we have
gone then we would never have gone to the counter
where you would have given the daily bill
where you would have paid the money, that is why perhaps
we do not know how
critical the hospital and hospitalization situation is
and this is the situation where a person is in
trauma suffering with mental and physical trauma and
the family is suffering from financial
trauma, emotional trauma and stress
to provide the best medical facility to that
important family member if you do not want to
face such a critical
situation so please insure yourself
today so now moving further into health insurance this
is a concept but let us
talk further in the concept TNC everything depends
upon the terms and conditions
so from the very first day accident
related hospitalization will be covered today if my
policy is issued then from that day from the very
first day from the very first minute
After issuing my policy, hospitalization
due to accident is
covered from 31st day onward. For
30 days before 31st day, only accident will be covered and
from 31st day new diseases will be covered.
Now you will understand. Now you will think what is a new disease. A
new disease is that disease which does
not exist in me from the time of my birth till date. Even if it does, I do
not know. So to get its clarification,
we will have to understand pre-assisting disease.
So, pre-assisting disease is covered
by some companies after four years. Some companies are covering pre-existing after three
years and some companies are covering after two
years and even one year. But this
one year and two year
policy is a little more. If your condition is bad
then you do not get the
policy. So, what does this pre-assisting
mean? Whatever problems I have had from the time of my birth till the
day I took the policy, I have to declare each and everything
to ensure that
my claim would be entertained by my
company.  The company will pay the claim in future
whenever I face any problem. Otherwise I will
not tell you. Many people are often
victims of mis-selling.
In India, people say that do not write anything, we will look into it later.
Understand that every insurance company has a
proper vigilance team. Please do not make such
mistakes. Do not waste your
money because the company's policy cancellation clause
simply says that if you have miswritten anything, if you have hidden
any information, if
you have hidden any fact, then the
company is liable to cancel your policy and
not to pay your
claim. And the money that you have paid for so many years
in the form of premium, you will not get that
back. So please declare each and everything. So now the
company will
decide whether any further test
is required or not, whether I want to take the policy or
not, if I want to take it, then how much waiting
period should be imposed. Let that company decide, but everything should be
on black and white.
Whatever things you have, these are promises because
Insurance is all we are selling a promise
on a piece of paper and that paper has only two
things one is the term and condition that is the
policy word from the company side and
from your side that is the proposal form when
both these things are combined then a policy is issued
so to strengthen it please
declare each and everything and please ask all the
term and condition from that particular
advisor and
broker with us you are taking the policy for
which you are giving responsibility so
we were talking about pre existing diseases so
pre existing disease would be covered after
four years and may be covered after two years
and one year depends upon policy to
policy that too then if I have declared then
please note if you have
not declared then there is a policy cancellation
now read this clause carefully
and every company has this
so moving further I repeat it once again
from the
Accident related hospitalization will be covered from the very first day from
31 days onwards New
disease plus accident will be covered after
three or four years depending on your policy to
policy Prior assisting is covered if you have
declared
right This is the waiting period
and there is one waiting period of two
years and one year depending on your policy to
policy That is for specific illnesses which the
company calls carry forward diseases
In medical terminology also such diseases are
called carry forward diseases which are
not risky by nature and do not develop immediately
and even if they develop then they do
not reach that stage where surgery is required
So to avoid fraud the company has
included this clause
For example cataract, cataract, black or
white cataract It is not such that it will
develop in a single day, it will develop in a month,
it takes years to develop
for example knee replacement, hip
replacement Now knee suddenly  It will not get damaged, it will take
years, pain will start, gradually it will become
worse and gradually after 10 years, it will
reach a situation where
replacement will be required, that is why the company
covers it after two years, any kind
of joint replacement right but due to
accident, everything is covered from one day
moving further, any kind of
logical issue related to any female is
covered after two years, for example,
cyst, uterus removal, this thing is covered after two years,
any kind of urinary tract related
problem to
male, as with increasing age,
urinary problems start occurring, there is
problem in urine,
so male related, all urinary tract
related problems will be covered after
two years, so after two years, this problem
is covered, for example, prostate
problem and any kind of urinary
tract related problem, after two years,
any kind of stone  Iron,
gall bladder stone, kidney stone and pancreas
stone are covered after two years. It is
not that the stone will develop immediately, it takes
time to develop. It takes
time for the
moving forward. Nutty related problems
like nose, throat, sinus problems, nasal
problems are covered after two years. They do
not develop immediately and do
not appear in life threatening situations, that is why it has been
kept in the period of two years. Gastric
related
problems after two years. Any kind of
internal continental problems.
Internal continental problem means a
jamad disease by birth defect. There are
many people who have two
types of defects internally at birth, one internal and one external. External
is a permanent
exclusion and it is never covered, but
internal continent means a jamad disease which is
a problem inside the internal organ, so
by nature there are 148 types of small defects.  There are
and there are bigger defects too like
having a single kidney or shrunken kidney, one kidney is
small and the other is big, the arteries are
not properly developed, there are many such problems in the eyes too, the
papilla is not developed, there is a
problem related to the urinary tract, there is some
internal defect by birth,
if it is already known then we have to
tell the company, it will depend whether the company will
provide the policy or not, if it does not provide then it is a good
thing, your premium will not be lost, if it
provides then you would be covered and if we do
not know and we come to know later
because often it comes to know only later as the age
increases, for example, there is a
hole in the heart, when the child is small, it is
not known why there is a problem in the heart, the
size of the heart is also small, the size of the hole
is also small, as the age increases the size of the heart will
also increase, the size of the hole will also increase automatically, so the
problem starts coming, then it gets
known on the latest SS also, many people come to know at the
age of 60 that they have a single kidney
by
birth, this costs a lot of crores, lakhs and crores  It
comes sot i cover after two years.
Apart from this, if we talk about any type
of piles, if we talk about fistula, it is
covered after two years. Any type
of thyroid is covered after two years.
So those are the waiting periods mentioned
over
here. If you have any doubt anywhere,
please speak to us. Moving further, the
waiting period is completed. Now,
permanent
exclusion is very important. So, the
first biggest exclusion that we all have to keep in
mind is alcohol, smoking,
drugs and any kind of
intoxicant, if you use it and due to that,
any complication comes in the body and any
claim comes in the long term, then that is
not covered. That is a permanent
exclusion. External continental defect,
as I told you, external
continental defect is not covered.
External continental defect is that the
hand is crooked by birth, it has to be straightened,
correction has to be done. There is an extra finger,
like Hrithik.  Caution:
Obesity related
problems are not covered.
Aging and pubic surgery is not
covered. Maternity is a permanent exclusion but it
can be an additional feature on special policies
by paying an additional amount. But it is a permanent
exclusion. Dental is a permanent
exclusion. Any dental related problem you
want to get fixed is not covered. Till now, no
one in the world has a dental policy for
any kind of
evaluation purpose. I
go to the hospital only for a check-up
and there was some identification
problem there, there was
no need for hospitalization. That is also not
covered. Please do not fall into the trap of the hospital people.
They say that you have health
insurance, you should get admitted and then you have to see whether
I really
need hospitalization or not.
For small colds, a
gentleman asked me that sir, please make a video in
which normal fever is also covered and
my cold and cough also.  It may be covered.
No my dear, it is not covered for
permanent
abuse. So please understand these conditions where
you will never get a claim on these conditions.
Self-injury: If I commit self-injury,
try to kill myself
or injure myself in anger, that is not
covered. I attempt suicide, that is not covered. I
try to do something against the law, I
drink and drive, I meet with an accident, that is
not
covered. So please be aware,
please take care of your life responsibly and live
a healthy and
prosperous life. Leave all your worries with health
insurance
and insure yourself and your
family. So let's talk about hospitalization again.
24 hours of hospitalization is
mandatory, but day care procedures
are many such treatments where there is
no need to be admitted for 24 hours and
in that situation, due to advancement
of technology, where it used to take three days to four days for
cataract operation,
for stone operation  Today, in three to four hours,
everything is relieved and you are sent home.
So, technology has advanced itself a lot and for
such procedures
where surgery is being done
and that procedure is being done under advanced technology and there is
no need to be admitted for 24 hours, then
that is also a part of the claim.
So
for detailed discussion on products, we will
create a
series, separate series. I
hope the concept of health insurance is
clear. So today I talked about health to
hospitalization. Today you are healthy, if
God forbid, you have to go for hospitalization tomorrow, then
what are the expenses incurred in the hospital, how much is the cost per day
and how big is that expense on your financial planning,
your future and your assets, even on
your property.
So please transfer that entire risk to
the
company but by
assuring all the facts and figures in your
proposal form and by understanding all the
terms and conditions,
so you can live
life without
tension, so you can live a life with no worries,
so I wish you the best. Stay in touch.
Progressive stay healthy and invest
wisely and protect your loved ones with the
right insurance coverage with high sum
so I will cover an additional part in this which
I will also make a detailed discussion on
which high sum high sum means if you are
going with lakh of policy please also try
to check the premium for 50 lakh and 50
crore then you will see that there is
not a huge gap
so this point will give you a very
clear understanding about high sum should
and I will share a detailed video for the
importance of high sum should with all the
logicians and all wish you all the best stay
connected please kindly share subscribe
and make this video reach all those people
so that we can spread the right information to as many of
your friends as possible and to
every corner of this country and
save people from mischief that is my main
motive thank you so much all the best
[Music]